One person after another gathered around the two.
Centuries ago there lived—
“A king!” my little readers will say immediately.
He struck a most solemn blow upon the piece of wood.
Mastro Cherry grew dumb, his eyes popped out of his head, his mouth opened wide, and his tongue hung down on his chin.
As soon as he regained the use of his senses, he said, trembling and stuttering from fright:
“I am teaching the ants their A B C’s.”
“Good luck to you!”
“What brought you here, friend Geppetto?”
“Here I am, at your service,” answered the carpenter, raising himself on to his knees.
“This morning a fine idea came to me.”
“Let’s hear it.”
“Bravo, Polendina!” cried the same tiny voice which came from no one knew where.
On hearing himself called Polendina, Mastro Geppetto turned the color of a red pepper and, facing the carpenter, said to him angrily:
“Why do you insult me?”
“Who is insulting you?”
“You called me Polendina.”
“I did not.”
And growing angrier each moment, they went from words to blows, and finally began to scratch and bite and slap each other.
When the fight was over, Mastro Antonio had Geppetto’s yellow wig in his hands and Geppetto found the carpenter’s curly wig in his mouth.
“Give me back my wig!” shouted Mastro Antonio in a surly voice.
“You return mine and we’ll be friends.”
“I swear to you I did not do it!”
“It was I, of course!”
“It’s the fault of this piece of wood.”
“I did not throw it!”
“Geppetto, do not insult me or I shall call you Polendina.”
“Idiot.”
“Polendina!”
“Donkey!”
“Polendina!”
“Ugly monkey!”
“Polendina!”
As soon as he reached home, Geppetto took his tools and began to cut and shape the wood into a Marionette.
No sooner was it finished than it began to laugh and poke fun at him.
“Stop laughing!” said Geppetto angrily; but he might as well have spoken to the wall.
“Stop laughing, I say!” he roared in a voice of thunder.
At that unexpected trick, Geppetto became very sad and downcast, more so than he had ever been before.
And he wiped away a tear.
Pinocchio saw the Carabineer from afar and tried his best to escape between the legs of the big fellow, but without success.
The Carabineer grabbed him by the nose (it was an extremely long one and seemed made on purpose for that very thing) and returned him to Mastro Geppetto.
Some said one thing, some another.
No, children, you are mistaken.
Once upon a time there was a piece of wood.
It was not an expensive piece of wood.
Far from it.
This has come in the nick of time.
He grasped the hatchet quickly to peel off the bark and shape the wood.
But as he was about to give it the first blow, he stood still with arm uplifted, for he had heard a wee, little voice say in a beseeching tone:
Please be careful!
What a look of surprise shone on Mastro Cherry’s face!
He turned frightened eyes about the room to find out where that wee, little voice had come from and he saw no one!
He looked under the bench—no one!
He peeped inside the closet—no one!
He searched among the shavings—no one!
Oh, I see!” he then said, laughing and scratching his Wig.
It can easily be seen that I only thought I heard the tiny voice say the words!
Where did that voice come from, when there is no one around?
Might it be that this piece of wood has learned to weep and cry like a child?
I can hardly believe it.
Here it is—a piece of common firewood, good only to burn in the stove, the same as any other.
Yet—might someone be hidden in it?
If so, the worse for him.
With these words, he grabbed the log with both hands and started to knock it about unmercifully.
He listened for the tiny voice to moan and cry.
Stop it!
Oh, stop it!
At the words, the door opened and a dapper little old man came in. His name was Geppetto, but to the boys of the neighborhood he was Polendina,* on account of the wig he always wore which was just the color of yellow corn.
Geppetto had a very bad temper.
Woe to the one who called him Polendina!
My legs.
I thought of making myself a beautiful wooden Marionette.
It must be wonderful, one that will be able to dance, fence, and turn somersaults.
With it I intend to go around the world, to earn my crust of bread and cup of wine.
I suppose you think I did!
Mastro Antonio, very glad indeed, went immediately to his bench to get the piece of wood which had frightened him so much.
Is this the gentle way, Mastro Antonio, in which you make your gifts?
Little as Geppetto’s house was, it was neat and comfortable.
It was a small room on the ground floor, with a tiny window under the stairway.
The furniture could not have been much simpler:
a very old chair, a rickety old bed, and a tumble-down table.
A fireplace full of burning logs was painted on the wall opposite the door.
The legs and feet still had to be made.
I deserve it!” he said to himself.
I should have thought of this before I made him.
When his legs were limbered up, Pinocchio started walking by himself and ran all around the room.
He came to the open door, and with one leap he was out into the street.
At last, by sheer luck, a Carabineer* happened along, who, hearing all that noise, thought that it might be a runaway colt, and stood bravely in the middle of the street, with legs wide apart, firmly resolved to stop it and prevent any trouble.
The little old man wanted to pull Pinocchio’s ears.
Geppetto looks like a good man,” added another, “but with boys he’s a real tyrant.
They said so much that, finally, the Carabineer ended matters by setting Pinocchio at liberty and dragging Geppetto to prison.
